Standard Tool Records
Standard Tool Records
1940-1969
Standard Tool (Leominster, Mass.)
5.5 linear ft.
This collection contains drawings of comb designs created for different companies; publications; and photographic prints and negatives of molds, machinery, factory interiors and building exteriors.
2651159
Biographical History
Lionel B. Kavanaugh (1889-1991) and Robert Stowell founded Standard Tool in Leominster, Mass, in 1911. The company made molds and presses for injection molding.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Standard Tool Records contains drawings of comb designs created for different companies; publications; and photographic prints and negatives of molds, machinery, factory interiors and building exteriors.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arranged into series by format and chronologically within. The photographs and negatives are arranged numerically by the numbers appearing on them.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Kavanaugh, Lionel B.; Standard Tool (Leominster, Mass.) -- Archives.; Plastics industry and trade.; Plastics -- Molds.; Combs.; Drawings (visual works); Photographs.; Publications.; Negatives (photographs); Manufacturing.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008. Originally, photographs and publications gift of Abraham Brangrazi, 1989; remainder from unknown source.
Inventory
- Drawings
  - Comb, 1940-1950; bound volume of technical drawings of comb molds for different molding companies; 1 volume (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Machinery, undated; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - People, 1981; photo of Lionel Kavanaugh (Box 2)
  - Prints of machinary and equipment, 1945-1969
    - Unnumbered (Box 3)
    - #61-157 (Box 3)
    - #158-307 (Box 4)
    - #309-428 (Box 5)
    - Unnumbered (Box 6)
    - #71-436 (Box 7)
  - Negatives of machinary and equipment, 1945-1969
    - #61-152 (Box 8)
    - #153-245 (Box 9)
    - #246-313 (Box 10)
    - #314-380 (Box 11)
- Publications
  - Company, 1955-1956; 1959,; undated; employee newsletters, brochures and technical booklets related to Standard Tool, Detroit Mold Engineering Co., and Guy Harvey; Industry magazine (Box 2)